Well, this is such an honor. And it's wonderful to be
حسناً، يشرفني ويسعدني أن أكون
in the presence of an organization that is really making a difference in the world.
ضمن منظمة تحدث وبحق فرقاً في العالم.
And I'm intensely grateful for the opportunity to speak to you today.
وأنا ممتنة لفرصة التحدث معكم اليوم.
And I'm also rather surprised, because when I look back on my life
وأيضاً أنا مندهشة لأنني عندما أتطلع إلى ماضي حياتي
the last thing I ever wanted to do was write, or be in any way involved in religion.
فإن آخر ما أردت فعله هو الكتابة أو الانخراط بأي شكل من الأشكال في الدين.
After I left my convent, I'd finished with religion, frankly.
إذ بعد مغادرتي الدير فإنني وبكل صراحة خلصت من الدين.¥
I thought that was it.
وظننت أن هذه هي النهاية.
And for 13 years I kept clear of it. I wanted to be an English literature professor.
وبعد مضي 13 عاماً بقيت بعيدة عنه وأردت أن أكون أستاذة في الأدب الإنجليزي.
And I certainly didn't even want to be a writer, particularly.
وفجأة لم أرغب حتى في أن أكون كاتبة على وجه التحديد.
But then I suffered a series of career catastrophes,
وعانيت بعدها من مشاكل جمة في العمل.
one after the other, and finally found myself in television. (Laughter)
واحدة تلو الأخرى ووجدت نفسي على حين غرة في التلفاز.
I said that to Bill Moyers, and he said, "Oh, we take anybody." (Laughter)
وقلت ذلك لبيل مويرز فقال" أوه، نحن نأخذ الجميع".
And I was doing some rather controversial religious programs.
وكنت أقدم بعض البرامج الدينية المثيرة للجدل إلى حد ما.
This went down very well in the U.K., where religion is extremely unpopular.
ولقد كان ذلك يسير بشكل جيد في المملكة المتحدة حيث الدين غير سائد.
And so, for once, for the only time in my life, I was finally in the mainstream.
وهكذا وللمرة الأولى في حياتي كنت وأخيراً مع التوجه السائد.
But I got sent to Jerusalem to make a film about early Christianity.
ولكنني بُعِثْت إلى القدس لتصوير فيلم حول العصور المسيحية الأولى.
And there, for the first time, I encountered the other religious traditions:
وهناك وللمرة الأولى واجهت التقاليد الدينية الأخرى:
Judaism and Islam, the sister religions of Christianity.
اليهودية والإسلام وهما ديانتان شقيقتان للمسيحية.
And while I found I knew nothing about these faiths at all --
ووجدت أنني لا أعلم شيئاً عن هاتين العقيدتين،
despite my own intensely religious background,
على الرغم من معلوماتي الدينية العميقة.
I'd seen Judaism only as a kind of prelude to Christianity,
وكنت أنظر لليهودية على أنها مقدمة للمسيحية،
and I knew nothing about Islam at all.
ولم أعلم شيئاً عن الإسلام.
But in that city, that tortured city,
ولكن في تلك المدينة، تلك المدينة المعذبة،
where you see the three faiths jostling so uneasily together,
ترى العقائد الثلاث هذه تتصادم وبشكل مضطرب للغاية معاً،
you also become aware of the profound connection between them.
كما وتصبح واعياً مدركاً للرابطة العميقة بينها.
And it has been the study of other religious traditions that brought me back
وكانت دراسة تقاليد الديانات الأخرى هي ما أعادني
to a sense of what religion can be, and actually enabled me
لفهم ما يمكن أن يكون عليه الدين، وحقيقًا فلقد جعلتني
to look at my own faith in a different light.
أنظر إلى إيماني من وجهة نظر مختلفة.
And I found some astonishing things in the course of my study
واكتشفت بعض الأمور المذهلة خلال سياق دراستي
that had never occurred to me. Frankly, in the days when I thought I'd had it with religion,
لم تخطر ببالي، وبكل صراحة في الايام التي ظننت فيها إنني وفق الدين،
I just found the whole thing absolutely incredible.
وجدت الأمر كله غاية في الروعة.
These doctrines seemed unproven, abstract.
وبدت تلك العقائد غير مثبتة ونظرية
And to my astonishment, when I began seriously studying other traditions,
ولدهشتي، فعندما بدأت جدياً دراسة التقاليد الأخرى،
I began to realize that belief -- which we make such a fuss about today --
بدأت أعي أن ذلك المعتقد أو الإيمان الذي نقوم بإحداث ضجة كبيرة حوله--
is only a very recent religious enthusiasm
هو فقط حماس ديني حديث للغاية
that surfaced only in the West, in about the 17th century.
ظهر في الغرب وحده، في حوالى القرن السابع عشر.
The word "belief" itself originally meant to love, to prize, to hold dear.
وكانت كلمة "معتقد" أو "إيمان" تعني بحد ذاتها أن تحب وتقدر وتعز.
In the 17th century, it narrowed its focus,
وفي القرن السابع عشر تم تضييق نطاقها،
for reasons that I'm exploring in a book I'm writing at the moment,
لأسباب أكشفها في كتاب أقوم بتأليفه حالياً،
to include -- to mean an intellectual assent to a set of propositions, a credo.
للتضمين - بقصد اعتلاء فكريّ لمجموعة من المقترحات: أي عقيدة.
"I believe:" it did not mean, "I accept certain creedal articles of faith."
"أنا أؤمن" - لم تعن "أنا أقبل بعض الأمور العقائدية للإيمان والعقيدة".
It meant: "I commit myself. I engage myself."
بل عنت: أتعهد شخصياً، وأنخرط".
Indeed, some of the world traditions think very little of religious orthodoxy.
وبالفعل، بعض معتقدات وتقاليد العالم تفكر قليلاً في الأرثوذكسية الدينية.
In the Quran, religious opinion -- religious orthodoxy -- is dismissed as "zanna:"
في القرآن فإن الرأي الديني أي --الأرثوذكسيةالدينية-- لا يتم الأخذ به إذ يكون ظناً:
self-indulgent guesswork about matters that nobody can be certain of one way or the other,
فهو تخمين ذاتي لأمور لا يمكن لأحد التأكد منها بطريقة أو بأخرى
but which makes people quarrelsome and stupidly sectarian. (Laughter)
ولكنه يثير الخلافات بين الأشخاص ويحدث وبغباء الطائفية.
So if religion is not about believing things, what is it about?
إذن، إن كان الدين لا يتمحور حول تصديق الأمور فعلى ماذا يتمحور؟
What I've found, across the board, is that religion is about behaving differently.
ما وجدت وبشكل شامل أن الدين هو حول التصرف بشكل مغاير مختلف.
Instead of deciding whether or not you believe in God, first you do something.
فبدل أن تقرر فيما إن كنت تؤمن بالله يتوجب عليك أولاً أن تفعل شيئاً
You behave in a committed way,
إذ تسلك وتتصرف بالتزام
and then you begin to understand the truths of religion.
ومن ثم تبدأ بفهم حقائق الدين.
And religious doctrines are meant to be summons to action;
والغاية من المذاهب الدينية استدعاء الأفعال
you only understand them when you put them into practice.
إذ يمكنك فهمها فقط عند وضعها قيد التنفيذ.
Now, pride of place in this practice is given to compassion.
والآن، يحظى التراحم بالصدارة في هذا التنفيذ والتطبيق.
And it is an arresting fact that right across the board,
وهو أمر مدهش يصوب ويصحح بشكل كامل
in every single one of the major world faiths, compassion --
في كل واحدة من العقائد العالمية الرئيسة، فالتراحم
the ability to feel with the other in the way we've been thinking about this evening --
هو المقدرة على الشعور مع الآخر وبالطريقة التي نفكر بها هذا المساء--
is not only the test of any true religiosity, it is also what will bring us
ليس فقط لاختبار التدين الحقيقي، ولكن ما يجعلنا
into the presence of what Jews, Christians and Muslims call "God" or the "Divine."
في حضور ما يدعوه اليهود والمسيحيون والمسلمون "الله" أو "الإلة"™
It is compassion, says the Buddha, which brings you to Nirvana.
ويقول بؤذا بأن التراحم هو الذي يوصلك إلى النيرفانا أي السعادة القصوى.
Why? Because in compassion, when we feel with the other,
لماذا؟ لأن التراحم يكون عندما نشعر بالآخرين
we dethrone ourselves from the center of our world and we put
فإننا نخلع أنفسنا عن محور عالمنا ونضع
another person there. And once we get rid of ego, then we're ready to see the Divine.
شخصاً آخر هناك. وحال التخلص من حب الذات عندئذ يمكننا ملاقاة الإلة.
And in particular, every single one of the major world traditions has highlighted -- has said --
وعلى وجه الخصوص فإن كل واحدة من المعتقدات العالمية الرئيسة قد شددت على أهمية كما ونادت
and put at the core of their tradition what's become known as the Golden Rule.
ووضعت في صلب معتقداتها ما أصبح يعرف بالقاعدة الذهبية.
First propounded by Confucius five centuries before Christ:
طرحها أولاً كونفوشيوس قبل المسيح بخمسة قرون:
"Do not do to others what you would not like them to do to you."
"لا تفعل بالآخرين ما لا تود أن يفعلوه بك".
That, he said, was the central thread which ran through all his teaching
وهذا وفق قوله هو الرابط الأساسي الذي يجري في كل تعاليمه
and that his disciples should put into practice all day and every day.
وعلى أتباعه وضعها قيد التطبيق طوال اليوم وكل يوم.
And it was -- the Golden Rule would bring them to the transcendent value that he called "ren,"
وإنها القاعدة الذهبية هي ما ستسمو بهم إلى قيمة أسماها "رين"
human-heartedness, which was a transcendent experience in itself.
فطبيعة القلب البشري تجربة سامية بحد ذاتها.
And this is absolutely crucial to the monotheisms, too.
وهو أمر ضروري للغاية للتوحيد أيضاً.
There's a famous story about the great rabbi, Hillel, the older contemporary of Jesus.
هناك قصّة مشهورة حول الحاخام العظيم هيليل وهو المعاصر الأكبر سنّا للمسيح
A pagan came to him and offered to convert to Judaism if the rabbi could
جاء وثني إليه وتعهّد اعتناق اليهودية إذا تمكن الحاخام من
recite the whole of Jewish teaching while he stood on one leg.
تلاوة التعليم اليهودي الكامل بينما هو يقف على ساق واحدة.
Hillel stood on one leg and said, "That which is hateful to you,
فوقف هيليل على ساق واحدة وقال "ما تكرهه،
do not do to your neighbor. That is the Torah. The rest is commentary.
لا تفعله لجارك، وهذه هي التوراة والباقي كله تعقيب وشرح.
Go and study it." (Laughter)
اذهب وادرسها".
And "go and study it" was what he meant.
وما عنى هو أن "يذهب ويدرسها".
He said, "In your exegesis, you must make it clear
لقد قال: "في التأويل الخاص بك، يجب أن توضح
that every single verse of the Torah is a commentary, a gloss upon the Golden Rule."
بأن كل آية من التوراة هي تعقيب وشرح ومسرد "للقاعدة الذهبية".
The great Rabbi Meir said that any interpretation of Scripture which
ولقد قال الحاخام الشهير ماير بأن أي تفسير للنصوص المقدسة والتي
led to hatred and disdain, or contempt of other people --
تؤدي إلى كره والتقليل من شأن الآخرين--¼
any people whatsoever -- was illegitimate.
الآخرين أيا كانوا -- هو غير شرعي.
Saint Augustine made exactly the same point.
هذا ولقد اشار القديس أوغسطين إلى نفس النقطة.
Scripture, he says, "teaches nothing but charity, and we must not leave
فلقد قال بأن "النصوص المقدسة لا تعلم سوى الإحسان ولا يتوجب علينا أن نترك
an interpretation of Scripture until we have found a compassionate interpretation of it."
أي تفسيراً للنصوص حتى نجد تفسيراً متعاطفاً متراحماً بها".
And this struggle to find compassion in some of these rather rebarbative texts
وهذا النضال لإيجاد التعاطف في بعض من تلك النصوص المثبطة نوعاً ما
is a good dress rehearsal for doing the same in ordinary life. (Applause)
هو تجربة جيدة لفعل المثل في الحياة اليومية.
But now look at our world. And we are living in a world that is --
ولكن انظر اليوم إلى عالمنا. فنحن نعيش في عالم--
where religion has been hijacked. Where terrorists cite Quranic verses to justify their atrocities.
حيث تتم عمليات الاختطاف باسم الدين وحيث الإرهابيون يتلون آيات من القرآن لتبرير أعمالهم الوحشية.
Where instead of taking Jesus' words, "Love your enemies.
حيث عوضاً عن العمل بكلمات المسيح "أحبوا أعداءكم.
Don't judge others," we have the spectacle of Christians endlessly judging other people,
ولا تدينوا الآخرين" إلا أننا نشاهد المسيحيين وباستمرار يدينون الآخرين،
endlessly using Scripture as a way of arguing with other people,
باستمرار مستخدمين النصوص المقدسة والآيات كوسيلة للمجادلة مع الأشخاص الآخرين
putting other people down. Throughout the ages, religion has been used to oppress others,
ومثبطين العزيمة. وقد تم عبر الأزمان استخدام الدين لقمع الآخرين،
and this is because of human ego, human greed.
وهذا بسبب حب الإنسان لذاته والجشع البشري.
We have a talent as a species for messing up wonderful things.
فنحن لدينا موهبة بإعتبارناأجناس تدمر وتخرب الأشياء الرائعة.
So the traditions also insisted -- and this is an important point, I think --
حيث أصرت التقاليد أيضًا -- وأعتقد أن هذه نقطة هامة --
that you could not and must not confine your compassion
بأنه لا يتوجب عليك تقييد تعاطفك وتراحمك
to your own group: your own nation, your own co-religionists,
إلى مجموعتك أو إلى أمتك أو إلى من يشاركك الدين،
your own fellow countrymen. You must have what one of the Chinese sages called "jian ai":
أو إلى أمثالك من المواطنين. بل يتوجب أن تملك ما أطلق عليه حكيم صيني "جيان آي":
concern for everybody. Love your enemies. Honor the stranger.
وهو الاهتمام بالآخرين. أحب أعداءك. أكرم الغريب.
We formed you, says the Quran, into tribes and nations so that you may know one another.
وكما ذكر في القرآن: "إنا خلقناكم شعوبا وقبائل لتعارفوا".
And this, again -- this universal outreach -- is getting subdued in the strident use of religion --
وهذا مرة أخرى يخمد -- هذا التواصل العالمي -- للاستخدام الشديد للدين --
abuse of religion -- for nefarious gains.
وإساءة استخدام الدين -- للمكاسب الشنيعة.
Now, I've lost count of the number of taxi drivers who,
والآن لم أعد أحصي عدد سائقي التاكسي الذين
when I say to them what I do for a living, inform me that religion
عندما أقول لهم ماذا أفعل لكسب معيشتي، يخبروني بأن الدين
has been the cause of all the major world wars in history. Wrong.
هو سبب كافة الحروب في العالم عبر التاريخ. وهذا خطأ.
The causes of our present woes are political.
فسبب مشاكلنا الحالية يعود للسياسة.
But, make no mistake about it, religion is a kind of fault line,
ولكن لا نخطئ، الدين هو أحد المفاهيم الكبيرة
and when a conflict gets ingrained in a region, religion can get sucked in
وعندما يصبح النزاع سارياً في منطقة فيمكن للدين أن يتوغل
and become part of the problem. Our modernity has been exceedingly violent.
ليصبح جزءاً من المشكلة. وقد أصبحت حداثتنا عنيفة بشكل متزايد.
Between 1914 and 1945, 70 million people died in Europe alone as a result of armed conflict.
فبين الأعوام 1914 و1945 توفي 70 مليون شخص في أوروبا وحدها نتيجة للنزاع المسلح.
And so many of our institutions, even football, which used to be a pleasant pastime,
وكذلك العديد من مؤسساتنا، حتى كرة القدم التي كانت تسلية لطيفة ممتعة
now causes riots where people even die.
يحدث فيها الآن أعمال الشغب التي يموت فيها الأشخاص.
And it's not surprising that religion, too, has been affected by this violent ethos.
وليس من المفاجئ أن الدين أيضاً قد تأثر بهذه الأخلاقيّات العنيفة.
There's also a great deal, I think, of religious illiteracy around.
وأعتقد بأن هناك أيضاً الكثير من الأميّة الدينية.
People seem to think, now equate religious faith with believing things.
فيبدو أن الناس الآن تساوي الإيمان الديني بتصديق الأشياء.
As though that -- we call religious people often believers,
كأن -- ندعو رجال الدين عادة بالمؤمنين
as though that were the main thing that they do. And very often, secondary goals
وكأن ذلك هو الأمر الرئيسي الذين يقومون به. وفي الغالب فإن الأهداف الثانوية
get pushed into the first place, in place of compassion and the Golden Rule.
يدفع بها إلى المكانة الأولى بدل التعاطف والتراحم والقاعدة الذهبية.
Because the Golden Rule is difficult. I sometimes -- when I'm speaking to
لأن القاعدة الذهبية صعبة. وأنا أحياناً عندما أكون أتكلم إلى
congregations about compassion, I sometimes see
التجمعات حول التعاطف والتراحم أرى في بعض الأوقات
a mutinous expression crossing some of their faces because
تعبير رافض على بعض الوجوه بسبب الدين
a lot of religious people prefer to be right, rather than compassionate. (Laughter)
فالكثير من رجال الدين يفضلون بأن يكونوا على صواب بدل من أن يكونوا متعاطفين متراحمين.
Now -- but that's not the whole story.
ولكن -- الآن ليست هذه هي الحكاية.
Since September the 11th, when my work on Islam suddenly propelled me
فمنذ الحادي عشر من سبتمبر/أيلول عندما دفعني عملي المتعلق بالإسلام
into public life, in a way that I'd never imagined, I've been able to sort of go all over the world,
إلى الحياة العامة بطريقة لم أتصورها يوماً، كنت قادرة على نحو ما من الذهاب إلى كافة أنحاء العالم،
and finding, everywhere I go, a yearning for change.
لأجد حيثما ذهبت الرغبة للتغيير.
I've just come back from Pakistan, where literally thousands of people came to my lectures,
لقد عدت لتوي من باكستان حيث جاء الآلاف فعلياً إلى محاضراتي
because they were yearning, first of all, to hear a friendly Western voice.
لأنهم كانوا يرغبون أولاً في سماع صوت غربي صديق.
And especially the young people were coming. And were asking me --
وبخاصة الشباب الصغار كانوا يأتون ويسألونني --
the young people were saying, "What can we do? What can we do to change things?"
كان الشباب يقول: "ماذا يمكن أن نفعل؟ ماذا يمكن أن نفعل لتغيير الأشياء؟".
And my hosts in Pakistan said, "Look, don't be too polite to us.
والمضيفون كان يقولون لي: "انظري، لا تكوني مهذبة للغاية معنا.
Tell us where we're going wrong. Let's talk together about where religion is failing."
قولي لنا أين أخطأنا. دعينا نتكلم معاً حول نواقصنا في الدين".
Because it seems to me that with -- our current situation is so serious
لأنه يبدو لي بأنه -- وبظروفنا الحالية الصعبة
at the moment that any ideology that doesn't promote a sense of global understanding
وفي الوضع الراهن أن أية أيدولوجية لا تعزز الفهم العالمي
and global appreciation of each other is failing the test of the time.
والتقدير العالمي لأحدنا الآخر فهي فاشلة من حيث اختبار الزمن.
And religion, with its wide following ... Here in the United States,
والدين بالاتباع الكبير له هنا في الولايات المتحدة--
people may be being religious in a different way, as a report has just shown --
يبدو الناس متدينين بطريقة مختلفة، كما دل التقرير على ذلك --
but they still want to be religious. It's only Western Europe that has retained its secularism,
ولكنهم لا يزالون يرغبون في التدين. حيث إن أوربا الغربية فقط التي تحتفظت بالعلمانية
which is now beginning to look rather endearingly old-fashioned.
والتي تبدأ الآن بالظهور وبشكل محبب كقديمة الطراز.
But people want to be religious, and religion should be made
ولكن الأفراد يرغبون في التدين، ويتوجب أن يبنى الدين
to be a force for harmony in the world, which it can and should be --
كقوة للانسجام في العالم، والتي يمكن ويتوجب أن تكون--
because of the Golden Rule.
نتيجة للقاعدة الذهبية.
"Do not do to others what you would not have them do to you":
"لا تفعل بالآخرين ما لا تود أن يفعلوه بك".
an ethos that should now be applied globally.
واحدة من الأخلاقيات التي يتوجب تطبيقها عالمياً.
We should not treat other nations as we would not wish to be treated ourselves.
لا يتوجب أن نعامل الأمم الأخرى بما لا نرغب أن نعامل به نحن أنفسنا.
And these -- whatever our wretched beliefs -- is a religious matter, it's a spiritual matter.
وهذه -- مهما كانت اعتقاداتنا بائسة -- هي مسألة دينية ومسألة روحية.
It's a profound moral matter that engages and should engage us all.
أنها موضوع سامي يتعلق ويجب أن يتعلق بنا جميعاً.
And as I say, there is a hunger for change out there.
وكما أقول، هناك جوع للتغيير في هذه الأماكن.
Here in the United States, I think you see it in this election campaign: a longing for change.
هنا في الولايات المتحدة، أعتقد أنك تراه في حملة الانتخابات هذه فهي رغبة للتغيير.
And people in churches all over and mosques all over this continent after September the 11th,
والأفراد في الكنائس وفي المساجد في كافة المناطق من هذه القارة بعد الحادي عشر من سبتمبر/أيلول
coming together locally to create networks of understanding.
يجتمعون محلياً لإيجاد قنوات للتواصل والفهم.
With the mosque, with the synagogue, saying, "We must start to speak to one another."
في المسجد والمعبد يقولون: "يجب أن نبدأ التحدث مع بعضنا بعضاً".
I think it's time that we moved beyond the idea of toleration and move toward appreciation of the other.
أعتقد بأنه قد حان الوقت للتقدم والتحرك إلى ما وراء فكرة التسامح والتحرك نحو تقدير الآخرين.
I'd -- there's one story I'd just like to mention.
أريد -- وهناك قصة واحدة أريد فقط سردها.
This comes from "The Iliad." But it tells you what this spirituality should be.
وهذه تأتي من "الإلياذة" ولكنها تخبرك عن كيفية ما يتوجب أن تكون عليه الروحانية.
You know the story of "The Iliad," the 10-year war between Greece and Troy.
أنتم تعرفون قصة "الإلياذة" حول الحرب التي استمرت 10 أعوام بين اليونان وطروادة
In one incident, Achilles, the famous warrior of Greece, takes his troops out of the war,
إنه وفي حادثة منها، يأخذ أخيل المحارب المشهور من اليونان قواته خارجاً للحرب،
and the whole war effort suffers. And in the course of the ensuing muddle,
وكله يعاني من المجهود الحربي، وخلال الفوضى التي تلت ذلك
his beloved friend, Patroclus, is killed -- and killed in single combat
حيث قتلت محبوبته باتروكلوس في معركة واحدة
by one of the Trojan princes, Hector. And Achilles goes mad with grief and rage and revenge,
من قبل هيكتور أحد أمراء طروادة، وعليه فإن أخيل يثور غضباً وحزناً ويرغب الانتقام
and he mutilates the body. He kills Hector, he mutilates his body
ويشوه الجسد -- إذ يقتل هكتور ويشوه جسده
and then he refuses to give the body back for burial to the family,
وبعد ذلك يرفض إعطاء جثته إلى عائلته لدفنها،
which means that, in Greek ethos, Hector's soul will wander eternally, lost.
وهذا يعني وفقاً للأخلاقيات اليونانية بأن روح هكتور ستهيم ضائعة إلى الأبد.
And then one night, Priam, king of Troy, an old man,
وفي أحد الأيام، يذهب بريام ملك طروادة وهو رجل مسن
comes into the Greek camp incognito, makes his way to Achilles' tent
في تستر إلى المعسكر اليوناني ويشق طريقه إلى خيمة أخيل
to ask for the body of his son.
ليسأله جثة ابنه.
And everybody is shocked when the old man takes off his head covering and shows himself.
ويصدم الجميع عندما يرفع الرجل المسن غطاء رأسه ويكشف عن نفسه.
And Achilles looks at him and thinks of his father. And he starts to weep.
ينظر أخيل إليه ويتذكر والده ويبدأ النحيب.
And Priam looks at the man who has murdered so many of his sons,
وينظر بريام إلى الرجل الذي قتل الكثير من أبنائه
and he, too, starts to weep. And the sound of their weeping filled the house.
ويبدأ هو بدوره النحيب، ويملأ صوت نحيبهما المنزل.
The Greeks believed that weeping together created a bond between people.
اعتقد اليونان بأن النحيب معاً والعويل يخلق رابطاً بين الناس.
And then Achilles takes the body of Hector, he hands it very tenderly to the father,
ومن ثم يأخذ أخيل جثة هكتور ويسلمها برفق إلى الوالد
and the two men look at each other, and see each other as divine.
وينظر الرجلان إلى بعضهما ويرى كل منها الآخر على أنه مخلوق إلهي مقدس.
That is the ethos found, too, in all the religions.
وهذه هي واحدة من الأخلاقيات التي نجدها أيضاً في جميع الديانات.
It's what is meant by overcoming the horror that we feel when we are under threat of our enemies,
هي ما يقصد به من التغلب على الرعب الذي نشعر به عندما نرزخ تحت تهديد أعدائنا،
and beginning to appreciate the other.
ونبدأ في تقدير الآخر.
It's of great importance that the word for "holy" in Hebrew, applied to God, is "Kadosh": separate, other.
إنه غاية في الأهمية أن كلمة "مقدس" في العبرية التي تطبق على الله هي "قادوش" التي تعني المنفصل أو الآخر.
And it is often, perhaps, the very otherness of our enemies which can
وعلى الغالب ربما غيرية أعدائنا يمكن أن
give us intimations of that utterly mysterious transcendence which is God.
تعطينا تنويهات حول ذلك التسامي والسمو الغامض الذي هو الله.
And now, here's my wish:
والآن، إليكم أمنيتي:
I wish that you would help with the creation,
أتمنى بأن تمدوا يد العون للبناء والخلق
launch and propagation of a Charter for Compassion,
إلى إطلاق ونشر ميثاق التعاطف والتراحم--
crafted by a group of inspirational thinkers from
الذي يصيغه مجموعة من المفكرين الملهمين من
the three Abrahamic traditions of Judaism, Christianity and Islam,
المعتقدات الإبراهيمية الثلاثة من اليهودية والمسيحية والإسلام
and based on the fundamental principle of the Golden Rule.
وبالاستناد إلى المبدأ الأساسي للقاعدة الذهبية.
We need to create a movement among all these people that I meet in my travels --
نحتاج إلى أن نؤسس حركة بين هؤلاء الأشخاص الذين أقابلهم في أسفاري --
you probably meet, too -- who want to join up, in some way,
وربما تقابل أيضاً -- من يريد الانضمام بنفس الطريقة،
and reclaim their faith, which they feel, as I say, has been hijacked.
لاستعادة إيمانهم الذين يشعرون به أنه تعرض -- كما أقول -- للاختطاف والسلب.
We need to empower people to remember the compassionate ethos,
نحن بحاجة إلى دعم وتمكين الاشخاص لتذكر أخلاقيات التعاطف والتراحم،
and to give guidelines. This Charter would not be a massive document.
ولتزويدهم بالإرشاد، فهذا الميثاق لن يكون وثيقة ضخمة هائلة.
I'd like to see it -- to give guidelines as to how to interpret the Scriptures,
أود ان أراه -- لأعطي إرشادات حول كيفية تفسير نصوصه،
these texts that are being abused. Remember what the rabbis and what Augustine
هذه النصوص التي يساء استخدامها. تذكر ماذا قاله الحاخام وأوغسطين
said about how Scripture should be governed by the principle of charity.
حول الكيفية التي يجب أن تضبط بها هذه النصوص المقدسة بمبدأ التعاطف والتراحم.
Let's get back to that. And the idea, too, of Jews, Christians and Muslims --
دعونا نعود إلى ذلك، وإلى الفكرة أيضاً حول اليهود والمسيحيين والمسلمين
these traditions now so often at loggerheads -- working together to
فهذه المعتقدات والتقاليد هي الآن وفي كثير من الأحيان على خلاف -- وتعمل معاً على
create a document which we hope will be signed by a thousand, at least,
إنشاء وثيقة نأمل أن توقع من قبل الآلاف على الأقل،
of major religious leaders from all the traditions of the world.
ومن قبل القادة الروحانيين الأساسيين ومن جميع المعتقدات والتقاليد في العالم.
And you are the people. I'm just a solitary scholar.
فأنتم العالم. أما أنا فمجرد عالمة وحيدة.
Despite the idea that I love a good time, which I was rather amazed to see coming up on me
وبرغم فكرة أنني أحب الأوقات الجيدة والتي ما زلت مندهشة من مروري بها
-- I actually spend a great deal of time alone, studying, and I'm not very --
-- فأنا فعلياً أمضي الكثير من وقتي وحيدة أدرس وأنا لست --
you're the people with media knowledge to explain to me how we can get this to everybody,
فانتم الأشخاص الذين لديهم المعرفة الإعلامية التي يمكن أن تشرحوا لي من خلاللها كيف يمكن أن نوصل هذا إلى كل فرد
everybody on the planet. I've had some preliminary talks,
في هذه الكوكب. لقد كان لي بعض المحادثات التمهيدية،
and Archbishop Desmond Tutu, for example,
والأسقف ديزموند توتو، ديزموند توتو على سبيل المثال،
is very happy to give his name to this, as is Imam Feisal Rauf, the Imam in New York City.
سعيد للغاية لإعطاء اسمه في هذا الأمر مثل الإمام فيصل رؤوف أمام مدينة نيويورك.
Also, I would be working with the Alliance of Civilizations at the United Nations.
كما سأعمل مع "تحالف الحضارات" التابع للأمم المتحدة
I was part of that United Nations initiative called the Alliance of Civilizations,
وكنت جزءاً من مبادرة الأمم المتحدة تلك التي أطلق عليها "تحالف الحضارات"،
which was asked by Kofi Annan to diagnose the causes of extremism,
والتي تم فيها سؤال كوفي عنان لتشخيص أسباب التطرف والتعصب،
and to give practical guidelines to member states about how to avoid the escalation of further extremism.
ولإعطاء توجيهات وإرشادات عملية إلى الدول الأعضاء حول كيفية تفادي تصاعد المزيد من التطرف والتعصب.
And the Alliance has told me that they are very happy to work with it.
وقد قال لي أعضاء التحالف بأنهم سعداء للغاية للعمل به.
The importance of this is that this is -- I can see some of you starting to look worried,
وأهمية ذلك هو كونه -- أستطيع أن أرى البعض منكم قد بدأ القلق،
because you think it's a slow and cumbersome body --
لأنكم تظنون أنها هيئة يميزها البطء والتبلد
but what the United Nations can do is give us some neutrality,
ولكن ما تستطيع الأمم المتحدة فعله هو منحنا الحيادية
so that this isn't seen as a Western or a Christian initiative, but that it's coming,
حتى لا ينظر إليها بأنها مبادرة غربية أو مسيحية بل إنها تأتي
as it were, from the United Nations, from the world --
كما هي من الأمم المتحدة ومن العالم--
who would help with the sort of bureaucracy of this.
من تراه يقدم يد المساعدة بهذا النوع من البيوقراطية كهذه.
And so I do urge you to join me in making -- in this charter --
ولهذا فإنني أحثكم على الانضمام لي لإنشاء -- هذه الوثيقة
to building this charter, launching it and propagating it so that it becomes --
في بناء هذه الوثيقة وإطلاقها ونشرها حتى تصبح
I'd like to see it in every college, every church, every mosque, every synagogue in the world,
أود رؤيتها في كل جامعة وفي كل كنيسة وفي كل جامع وفي كل معبد في العالم،
so that people can look at their tradition, reclaim it, and make religion a source of peace in the world,
حتى يتمكن الأشخاص من النظر لمعتقدهم والمطالبة به لاستعادته وجعل الديانة والدين مصدراً للسلام في العالم،
which it can and should be. Thank you very much. (Applause)
والذي هو أمر ممكن وواجب. وشكراً لكم جزيل الشكر.